Register of the John Richardson, Jr. papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Richardson, Jr. papers
1956-2005
2011C15
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, reports, memoranda, financial records, meeting materials, printed matter, and photographs relating to American foreign and cultural relations, international relief efforts, and the promotion of international democratic institutions.
Richardson, John, 1921-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Co-founder and Chair, American Committee for Aid of Poland; board member (Chairman Emeritus), National Endowment for Democracy.
1960-1961: President, International Rescue Committee
1961-1968: President, Free Europe Inc. (Radio Free Europe)
1969-1977: United States Assistant Secretary of State for Educational and Cultural Affairs
1971-1973: Acting Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs
1977-1978: Director of Social Research at the Center for Strategic and International Studies
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, reports, memoranda, financial records, meeting materials, printed matter, and photographs relating to American foreign and cultural relations, international relief efforts, and the promotion of international democratic institutions.
Free Europe Committee.; International Rescue Committee.; National Endowment for Democracy (U.S.); United States. Dept. of State.; Democracy.; International relief.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Relations.
- Correspondence, 1956-2003
  - Cooperative for American Remittances to Everywhere, 1959 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Dacrow Charitable Trust, 1959-1972 (Box-folder 1: 2-8)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes attached financial statements/receipts.
  - Foreign affairs, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Free Europe Committee/RFE, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Heber, Paul, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Relates to Heber's children's home for young Polish refugees, including funding information.
  - Hoover Institution, 1996, 2003 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Hungary, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - International Communications Project, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 2: 3-5)
  - International Rescue Committee, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - International Rescue Committee - Far East, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - International Rescue Committee - Jaanimets, 1960 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    Relates to an Estonian sailor called Jaanimets and publicity surrounding IRC assistance of him.
  - Next Century Initiative, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2: 9-10, 3: 1-2)
  - Thank you letters to Richardson, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Photographs, 1957, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  Includes personal photos of Richardson, photos of events/gatherings, and photos from political rallies.
- Printed Matter, 1976-2005
  - Jaanimets and International Rescue Committee, 1960 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - American Committee for Aid to Poland, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Deudney, Daniel, "Structured Liberalism: The Nature and Sources of Western Political Order,", 1995 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Fisher, Glen, "U.S. International Educational and Cultural Relations: Changing Factors in the Middle East and Africa,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Ikenberry, G. J., "Creating Liberal Order: The Origins and Persistence of Postwar Western Settlement,", 1995 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Ikenberry, G. J., "The Future of International Leadership,", 1995 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Ikenberry, G. J., "The Myth of the Post-Cold War Order,", 1995 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - National Endowment for Democracy board meeting, transcript of proceedings, 1983 December (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - National Endowment for Democracy board meeting, transcript of proceedings, 1984 September (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - National Endowment for Democracy board meeting, transcript of proceedings, 1984 December (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Odom, William, "How to Create a True World Order,", 1995 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Richardson, John, Institutional Innovation: Organizing for Better International Relationships, pamphlet, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Roth, R. L., "A New Spirit,", 1975 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - State Department, 1971-1976 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    Includes meeting agendas and copies of reports from the period when Richardson was Assistant Secretary of State for Education and Cultural Affairs.
  - World Learning Board of Trustees meeting, San Francisco, CA, minutes and related materials, 2004 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - World Learning Board of Trustees meeting, Washington, D.C., minutes and related materials, 2005 (Box-folder 4: 9)